A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1972-1979
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Secretary of Transportation, 1972-1979
The Library of Virginia
30965
5 cu. ft. (5 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Transportation, 1980 Novemeber 5.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of files related to transportation in Virginia, topics include legislations, Department of Motor Vehicles, highways, and aviation.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1979., Extent: 5 cu. ft. (5 boxes). (Box 1-5)
  Original arrangement of the agency has been maintained, which is generally alphabetical.
  - American Association of State Highway and Transportation Officials, 1979 Oct 13-16. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appalachian Power Company - Energy Seminar/Roanoke, Virginia, 1979 Oct 17. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Airports Authority, Virginia, undated. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Airports Authority, Virginia - Meetings, undated. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Asbestos - General, undated. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aviations - Airport Lannd Use/Seminar Workshop, undated. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aviation - Demonstration Program, State of Virginia, undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Aviation - Charlottesville/Albemarle Airport - Access Road, undated. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aviation - Federal Aviation Administration/Air Transportation Security Office, undated. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Aviation - Conference, 1979 Sept 9-12. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brown Boveri Corporation, undated. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Chesapeake Bay and Coastal Areas Management Signing Ceremony, 1979 Aug 22. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Civil Rights - Presidents Task Force, undated. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clean Air Act, undated. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Conference of State Depatments of Transportation - Membership List, undated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Conference of State Depatments of Transportation - Member States, undated. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Conference of State Depatments of Transportation - General, undated. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Conference of State Depatments of Transportation - Meeting in Washington D.C., 1979 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Crater Planning District Commission/Petersburg, Virginia, undated. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Crime Commission, Virginia State, undated. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dowden Terrace, Northren Virginia, undated. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Eastern Regional Internation Trade Seminar/New York, 1979 June 28. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Econometric Model, Virginia, undated. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Emergency Numbers 911, undated. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Emergency Medical Services Advisory Council (State Health Department), undated. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Emergency Medical Training Exercise, undated. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Office of Emergency and Energy Services - Hurricane Preparedness Symposium, Norfolk, 1979 June 5. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Office of Emergency and Energy Services - Ice Storm and Bad Weather, Southwest, Virginia, 1979 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Office of Emergency and Energy Services - Patrick and Henry Counties Flooding, 1979 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Office of Emergency and Energy Services - State Assistance to Victims of Small Disasters, 1979 Jan 6. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Emergency Services - National Catastrphic (flood) Insurance, undated. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Emergency Services - Resource Problems, GSA/FPA Reports, undated. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Energy - Virginia Energy Office: Lawson, undated. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Energy - Virginia Energy Resource Advisory Commission, undated. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Energy Division - Energy Task Force: H.R. Johnson, chairman, undated. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Energy - Gasohol, undated. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Energy - Gasohol Subcommittee of the House Committee: Studying Potential of Gasohol, undated. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Energy - Geothermal Energy (DOE briefing, movement of geothermal rigs), undated. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Emergency Services - Surplus Property Executive Orders, undated. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Firemen and Rescue Vehicles, Study volunteers, undated. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Four-Day Work Week (DMV Project and other 4 day material), undated. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fuel Economy Standards (US department of Transportation - light trucks), undated. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Federal - Defense Civil Preparedness Agency, undated. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Federal - Disaster Assistance Administration, undated. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Federal - Disaster Preparedness Assistance, application for, undated. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Federal Emergency Preparedness and response reorganization, undated. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Federal - Earthquake Hazards, undated. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Federal - Preparedness Agency - General Services Administration, undated. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Federal - Emergency Preparedness, Office of, undated. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Gas - Liquefied Natural: Federal Safety Standards, undated. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Governor Godwin - Statement to General Assembly: goals, objectives and policies, 1978-1980. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Governor's Cabinet - Public Cabinet Meetings, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Governor's People's Meeting - Lebanon, Virginia, 1978 July 17. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Governor's People's Meeting - Richmond, Virginia, 1978 Oct 18. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Governor's People's Meeting - Fairfax, Virginia, 1978 Aug 8. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Governor's People's Meeting - Virignia Beach, Virginia, 1978 May 16. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Governor, Lieutenant John N. Dalton, undated. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Heliport - MCV, undated. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Herrity, John, undated. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Highway Allocation - House Joint Resolution 172, undated. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Firemen and Rescue Vehicles, Study volunteers, 1979 Oct 31-Nov 2. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Housing and Urban Development - Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Intergovernmental Affairs - Special Programs (Lynn Curry) Office, undated. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Inspection, Motor Vehicles (Semi-Annual vs. Annual), undated. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Interstate 66 - Wage Rates, undated. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Interstate 66 - US Department of Transportation: secretary decision, undated. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Interstate 66 - Concepts for the I-66 Traffic Management Systems, undated. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Joint Legislative Audit Review Commission - Capital Outlay Process, undated. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Joint Legislative Audit Review Commission - Sunset Legislation and Zero Base Budget, undated. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Johnson, Hiram R., undated. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - land - State-Land Use Task Force, undated. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Leases - State Facilities (Agencies and Institutions), undated. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Leesburg Airport, undated. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Legislation Transportation Session - Proposals: General, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Legislation - Self-Insurance (Senate Joint Resolution 88), 1979. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Legislation - Emergency Services and Disaster Law, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Legislation - Highways and Transportation: General, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Legislation - Caboose Law, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Legislation - Coal Haul Roads in Southwest Virginia, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Legislation - House Bill 602: Highways Maintenance Payments, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Legislation - Department of Motor Vehicles: General, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Legislation - DMV Position Paper, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Legislation - Railroad, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Legislation - Transportation Safety Department, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Legislation - Aviation Department Senate Bill 250/Senate Bill 76 (no. 1), 1979. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Legislation - Aviation Department Senate Bill 250/Senate Bill 76 (no. 2), 1979. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Legislation - Aviation: Senate Bill 76 Master Copy of Testimony, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Legislation - department of Aviation, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Mid-Atlantic Federal Regional Council, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miller, Robert L., Jr. (Maryland Construction Executive), 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Military Affairs - Office Space Move, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Military Assistance to Safety and Traffic (MAST), 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Motor Vehicles - Branch Offices: Eastern Shore, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Motor Vehicles - Branch Offices: Martinsville, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Motor Vehicles - Branch Offices: Petersburg, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Motor Vehicles - Branch Offices: Roanoke, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Motor Vehicles - Branch Offices: West End, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Motor Vehicles - Branch Offices: Winchester, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Motor Vehicles - Driver Improvement Program, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Motor Vehicles - License Tags Production, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Motor Vehicles - Update Question, 1978 Jan. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Motor Vehicles - Site Selection for Branch Offices, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Motor Vehicles - Personnel, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - National Governor's Association - File 2, 1978. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - National Governor's Association - Meeting: Louisville, Kentucky, 1979 July 8. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - National Governor's Association - Policy Positions, 1978-1979. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - National Governor's Association - Supplement, 1979. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - National Radio Quiet Zone, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Outdoor Advertising - Committee: Sight of Public Highways, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Paint Manufacture (corrections/ Virginia Department of Transportation and Highways), 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Personnel and Training, 1972-1978. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Personnel - Study of Personnel Management: House Joint Resolution 64, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Personnel - Position Approvals, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Perosnnel - Establishing and filling Positions, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Personnel - Management Advisory Committee, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Petroleum Project, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Pollution - Control Strategies, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Pollution - Reduction in Air Pollution: House Joint Resolution 254, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Pollution - Air Study Commission: Chaired by Senator H.P. Anderson, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Ril - Eastern Shore, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rail - Federal Railroad Administration, 1972-1977. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Rail - Federal Railroad Administration Meeting, 1978 Apr 11. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Rail - Richmond, Fredericksburg, and Potomac Railroad Company, 1978-1979. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Rail - State Rail Plan, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Rail - Tidewater Rail: Virginia Beach, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Secondary Road System of Virginia - Highways, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Southwest Virginia Roads, 1978 May-June. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Southwest Virginia Legislative Tour - Highways, 1978 Nov. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Tanker Standards Rulemaking Petition, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 3-M Company, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Transportation Safety Advisory Committee Annual Meeting, 1979 May 24. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Transportation Advisory Council Meeting, 1979 Mar 13. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Transportation Advisory Council Meeting - First, 1978 Nov 28. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - United States Department of Transportation - National Highway Safety Advisory Committee, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Agribusiness Council, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Association of Rescue Squads, Inc., 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1972-1978. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Virignia Advisory Committee on Aviation, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Wide Loads - 14 foot housing units, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Yorktown Bicentennial Committee, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Assistant to the Secretary of Transportation - Applicants: Replacement of H. Johnson, 1978-1979. (Box 5, Folder 19)